um one of the best ways to know if you
have the chops for a tech career is to
judge your own ability to do math and I
have a story about
this uh maths you know maths the story
is about math
um pretty much everybody has to do math
at some point uh in in every career and
culture I'm sorry in every uh country
and culture learning math is a core part
of of the educational curriculum no
matter what no matter where you are and
my the story goes like this so my uh my
son and I who was helping me do some
teaching went on to teach at a private
school and some other things um we were
struggling because while we were at
skill stack we noticed that there were
some people in the same group actually
same age that were really able to pick
up computer programming they had no
problem with it and there were others
that looked at us like with really blank
stairs and and it was It was kind of
interesting in fact I you know I called
The Learning lab skill secc was kind of
a learning lab and they yeah they're
talking about the passion thing from the
other video that's cool too so anyway we
were you know we were like all the all
the people had the same level of
intelligence they had the same uh
passion I mean they'd all been more or
less vetted before they were allowed to
come in to some degree and and we were
still struggling to figure out you know
as we were I can't remember we were
talking but we were trying to figure out
why what was so
different and in fact we started asking
um there were a couple of outliers in
the group who were
so beyond uh everybody else their their
Pace at which they could pick up
specifically programming coding was so
much faster than than some of the other
ones and we're like What is different
what is distinguishing these people and
it was a very unscientific process but
we I started just asking them I had a
really great relationship with all of
them obviously and I was like I remember
one in particular I asked them I said yo
um I said you know Tim how do how did
you pick up computer programming so
quickly when you were young I mean you
were here when you were like N9 or 10
years old I mean you were really really
young and and how did you I mean what
and and he's like I don't know I just I
just did it you know I and I I kept
peppering him I was like what what else
did you do I mean
and and so
anyway back to the the part where my son
and I are talking with each other and we
started presenting a hypothesis that it
was math and we were saying okay it's
not age related because we have people
that are really young that are kicking
butt against people that are much older
and and you know but so could it be that
there's some kind of math exposure
that's different or something and we we
already knew that I mean the hypothesis
was that math because it teaches
functions you know F ofx = 2x + 1 um
that that it is you know computer
science in in in a very real way is a
sub science of mathematics I mean that
that is just true and the higher up you
get in I mean in terms of like
understanding how computers work the
more you understand you're just dealing
with math at a very uh at a very high
level and um so so I started asking and
uh yeah computer science is applied math
right and
so you know the the the premise of
learning how to think logically like
learn learning learning how a math works
like putting a thing in and getting
something out of it the concept of a
function very specifically that was the
the the data point that we were using to
assess uh who knew what you know and
that was also the thing that people look
at us like we had nine heads I remember
even trying to teach things like blockly
or scratch to to beginners they were
like you know they they couldn't if they
hadn't had algebra or even pre-algebra
they couldn't get it in their head that
there's this idea of putting some data
in a number or whatever and then that
machine it would come out on the other
side and so I I asked I asked you know
this this member directly I was like how
did did you learn math
early uh I mean what level of math are
you in now he goes well I'm just an
algebra now I like yeah but did you know
it already he goes yeah I'm like what do
you mean and he said well I learned it
myself like what it's like yeah I I
always want to learn it so I learned it
when I was like 10 or something so he
had gone on this internet on the
internet and I don't even remember how
and he taught himself algebra before he
ever even have an algebra class in
school which I could get down a whole
rabbit hole about why formalized
education for the masses is totally
screwed up because it doesn't keep up
with the pace of the people this this
person had taught the algeb by the time
they were in algebra they were totally
bored which is probably the one of the
reasons I saw them I saw a lot of people
who were bored by the by the formal
education system and they would come to
me and we would challenge them we would
you know push them on in their way but
the takeaway is that math was the
distinguishing feature so the the people
that were able to just really rock with
with with python functions and
procedures and stuff they had had a
certain amount of algebra so when you
said oh you're putting a thing in and
you're getting something out right and
again the melee ability of young age
brains absolutely totally down with that
um and whether it's because they want to
get good with Minecraft running their
own servers or whatever they learn so
much more in fact I think there's like a
really magical age uh between between 10
and uh 14 pretty much where the
especially for men
where you know the hormones start to
kick in and other distractions come up
they have the brain capacity to kind of
really understand all of this they're
also picking up math that if you are
trying to decide you have a young person
in your life that you're trying to
decide how to get them into the stuff
that is a really prime age between like
10 and 10 and 14 or so to really really
just go on the on the coding kind of
things uh and those activities because
they they will still be interesting to
them and they're going to discover like
you know cars and sports and girls and
stuff like that and you know it's from
my experience it's much hard fact people
a lot of times they would they would
leave and then they would come back uh
after they would come back at like 19 I
remember uh I had some some I had some
people come back literally uh after
college um because because of the
situations that were happening there um
anyway uh coming to yourself today I am
Whit uh we're in the middle of making
videos today so Whit thank you for the
invitation that that is all for today
for that video so the video is if you're
good at math you're probably going to be
a good programmer that's one factor